Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Library Oral History Collection AD.MC.023
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
NYU Abu Dhabi Library Oral History Project
2014
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
AD.MC.023
2.85 Terabytes
23 oral history interviews open for access
The NYUAD Oral History Collection contains video-recorded oral history interviews that were conducted with members of the New York University Abu Dhabi community during the spring, summer and fall terms of 2014. The collection includes preservation and access video copies, as well as accompanying edited transcripts. Interviewees include university students, faculty, and staff who were present during the first four years of operations.
Biographical / Historical
New York University Abu Dhabi was established in partnership with the Emirate of Abu Dhabi, and began offering undergraduate courses beginning in the Fall of 2010. While plans for a main campus on Abu Dhabi's Saadiyat Island were approved in March 2009, in December of that year an interim Downtown Campus (DTC) opened in Abu Dhabi city, and welcomed its inaugural class of 148 students in September 2010.
The NYUAD Oral History Project was a 2014 collaboration between the NYUAD Library and the Office of Human Resources. Project team members included Library Director, Virginia Danielson; Librarian for Research and Reference Services, Ilka Datig; Media Specialist and Videographer, Rebecca Pittam; and Tamu Al Islam, who at the time of the project was Director of HR Services, Strategy, and Engagement.
The subjects of this oral history collection are university students, faculty, and staff who were present during the first four years of operations. NYUAD community members were informally polled, and those who were identified as individuals "with interesting and unique knowledge of the early days" were invited to participate in a 30-minute to 1-hour video-recorded interview session. The resulting set of interviews represents those who agreed and were available. A first round of interviewing took place during the Spring 2014 semester, weeks ahead of the University's first commencement ceremonies. Additional interviews were recorded during Summer and Fall 2014.
Interviews were conducted in dedicated campus spaces in DTC, and later Saadiyat, with Ilka Datig, Rebecca Pittam, and Tamu Al-Islam (and sometimes others) also present as interviewers and facilitators.
Questions asked covered a range of topics, including questions about impressions, key moments, the physical environment, and individual memories.
The project formed a beginning effort to document the origins of NYUAD, with the goal "to begin the preservation of materials and memories related to the early days of NYUAD before they are lost or forgotten." Early project documentation notes this project as the initial effort to build and grow a University Archives, as participants were invited to add to other materials such as "yearbooks, born-digital items from social media, a collection of media coverage from both print and online sources, and any other memorabilia to which we can gain access."
Reference: (from original invitation letter to potential interviewees.) Reference: https://nyuad.nyu.edu/en/about/nyuad-at-a-glance/history.html
Scope and Contents
The NYUAD Oral History Collection contains video-recorded oral history interviews that were conducted with members of the New York University Abu Dhabi community during the spring, summer and fall terms of 2014. The collection includes preservation and access video copies, as well as accompanying edited transcripts. Interviews were conducted with administrative, faculty, staff, and student leaders who were identified as individuals in the NYUAD community "with interesting and unique knowledge of the early days." Each interview includes a summary of interview contents. Most interviews include accompanying textual transcriptions, available upon request.
This collection would be of interest to anyone who seeks information on the origins and history of NYU Abu Dhabi, an understanding of key moments and events in the first four years of its operations, and the reflections of a small representative cross-section of early NYUAD community members.
Arrangement
Interviews are arranged chronologically by date of interview.
Conditions Governing Access
Interviews that are open and unrestricted are available for viewing onsite in the Archives and Special Collections reading room, or temporary view-only remote access may be arranged. Access copies include low-resolution video and/or audio, edited caption files, and in most cases, transcriptions.
- Interview with Brett Heeger and Nils Lewis by Tamu Al-Islam and Ilka Datig (55:00), 17 Nov 2013; ADMC023_ref1; 55 minutes; 75 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref1)
  Scope and Contents
  Video-recorded session with Brett Hegeer, former NYUAD Program Coordinator and Special Assistant to the Provost; and Nils Lewis, NYUAD Program Coordinator then Manager of Faculty and Student Programs for the NYUAD Institute. Conducted by Ilka Datig, Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library, as well as Tamu Al Islam, Director of Human Resources Services, Strategy and Engagement.
  Nils and Brett describe their journey in the coordination of NYU Abu Dhabi as recent graduates and younger members of the team. They describe work on important projects like the Sheikh Mohamed Bin Zayed Scholars Program and the NYUAD Institute. The former gave them an opportunity to meet leaders in the political field and engage with Emirati students. For the Institute, they recall conducting extensive outreach to the community which was done manually throughout the city of Abu Dhabi at beaches and other locations. They also mention the importance of a connected Arab diaspora and Arab networks to sustaining the relationship between the Institute and the community. Many other instances also required a very hands-on approach on their part whether that was writing welcome cards for visitors or setting up the stage for a particular event. The pair also played the role of hosts to many groups and individuals who visited the institution as part of the recruitment process or for other programs. They discuss the adventures of learning to live in Abu Dhabi, experiencing the environment, local culture, religion and locating necessary spaces such as laundromats and supermarkets.
- Interview with Jordan Schulze by Ilka Datig (48:00), 27 Apr 2014; ADMC023_ref2; 48 minutes; 130 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref2)
  Video-recorded session with Jordan Schulze, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 senior student at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  In this session, Jordan Schulze shares his experience of applying to NYUAD while primarily planning to join the U.S. Air Force Academy. He reflects on the overarching feelings of excitement and nervousness before leaving the U.S. for the first time for the Candidate Weekend. Jordan reflects on his experience of seeing the yet unfinished dormitory rooms at Sama Tower and getting to know other students at breakfasts and while studying at the Library. He views the first sports victory of NYUAD and the first rain experience in the U.A.E. as important social events that helped to bring the student body together. Jordan reflects on his exploration of different academic areas and finding his own academic path in spite of the pressure from his family. He shares his experiences of participating in the university's first student production theater show, working as the Assistant Director for Rubén Polendo, interning at the Lincoln Center in New York and being a part of the RealAD Show. He talks about his academic experiences in relation to the courses he took and the class trips he went on. Jordan also discusses the specificities and difficulties of theater production in Abu Dhabi.
- Interview with Claudia Patricia Carrasco Valdich by Ilka Datig (35:00), 27 Apr 2014; ADMC023_ref3; 35 minutes; 97.42 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref3)
  Video-recorded session with Claudia (Patricia) Carrasco Valdich, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 senior student at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  In this session, Claudia describes her journey from the application process to her final days as a member of the Class of 2014. She includes her initial introduction to NYUAD, first impressions of the school and the cultural novelties and impressions of the city of Abu Dhabi. Claudia also discusses the various difficulties she experienced in this new and diverse environment, unforgettable moments with her schoolmates, especially with the RealAD show and with Dragon boating, and how she began to feel a changing sense of community.
- Interview with Emily Eagen by Ilka Datig (42:18), 27 Apr 2014; ADMC023_ref4; 42:18 minutes; 116.72 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref4)
  Video-recorded session with Emily Eagen, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 senior student at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  In this interview, Emily Eagen shares her story of applying to New York University Abu Dhabi and her Candidate Weekend experience. She shares a number of anecdotes related to her first days on campus, such as being afraid of leaving the Sama Tower residence, even to do grocery shopping, or feeling nervous about meeting her roommate, who was from a different personal and religious background. Emily recounts her first few weeks on campus filled with excitement and social events but also feeling stressed and homesick later in the first semester. She shares her positive first impressions of the city and reflects on the difficulties she faced in Abu Dhabi, mainly the dress code and the uncomfortable feeling caused by people's stares. Emily shares her experience of starting an informal Christian group on campus and participating in interreligious dialogues, which later grew to become the Interfaith Committee at NYUAD. She shares her concerns with the competitiveness of the University and the mental health of the students, especially with the suicidal inclinations among the student body. She then reflects on the Facebook arguments as being emblematic of the contemporary NYUAD, shares her experiences of participating in the RealAD Show and welcoming the freshman students to the community.
- Interview with Mohammed Omar by Ilka Datig (31:00), 27 Apr 2014; ADMC023_ref5; 31 minutes; 86.17 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref5)
  Video-recorded session with Mohammed Omar, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 student and 2011/2014 Student Body President at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  Mohammed Omar reflects on his time at NYU Abu Dhabi as he gets closer to graduation. He posits the idea that the student body is formed of two dichotomous groups - those who are accustomed to an international environment and those who had their first international experience at NYUAD. He also touches on his relationship to Abu Dhabi city as he began to explore the physical environment and appreciate its cosmopolitan nature. Omar's experience with community-building at NYUAD as well as within the Global Network of Universities is also important as he was a two-time Student Body President. He discusses the connections he was able to make at a personal level through his friendships, on an administrative level with faculty and staff, and up to the global level.
- Interview with Charlotte Wang by Ilka Datig (35:00), 4 May 2014; ADMC023_ref6; 35 minutes; 96.23 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref6)
  Viedo-recorded session with Charlotte Wang, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 senior student at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  In this session, Charlotte Wang shares her story of applying to and receiving an acceptance letter from NYU Abu Dhabi. She recalls her first impressions of Abu Dhabi, her Candidate Weekend experience, and her first day on campus, including meeting her roommates and being sleep deprived. Charlotte gives an overview of her first semester at NYUAD, reflects on the courses she took (Becoming Human; Chinese Language course; Economics; Foundations of the Modern Social Thought taught by Ivan Szelenyi) and reminisces about little things in her student life that she found exciting in her yearly student years (such as having sandwiches from plastic boxes for lunch). She offers her description of the school's physical environment (unoccupied spaces, specific hallway smell). Charlotte talks about her proudest accomplishments, including engaging with the community through the initiatives of ADvocacy and Ecoherence and writing her Capstone project. She also shares the difficulties and opportunities of community building in the early years of the university and advises future students to avoid the segmentation of the student body.
- Interview with Ramesh Jagannathan by Ilka Datig (38:00), 4 May 2014; ADMC023_ref7; 38 minutes; 103.12 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref7)
  Video-recorded session with Ramesh Jagannathan, former Associate Dean of Engineering, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  Ramesh Jagannathan describes his NYU Abu Dhabi journey as a major career and life shift from the corporate world. He talks about developing the engineering program at the University after working closely with colleagues at NYU in New York. He mentions what it means to be a global leader, and both the university's and his role in creating global leaders through the provision of resources for the former, and course creation and mentorship of bright minds in his case. He also touches on the academic difficulties of having a diverse student body with regard to their approach to learning, English proficiency and other factors which affect the standardisation of learning while also contributing to the success of the institution. He reflects on the growth he has seen in the University and in Abu Dhabi generally, moving from undersupplied laboratories to being at the forefront of research in the region, as an exercise in adaptability of the school's leaders and students.
- Interview with John Burt by Ilka Datig (32:00), 4 May 2014; ADMC023_ref9; 32 minutes; 87.63 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref9)
  Video-recorded session with John Burt, Associate Professor of Biology at NYUAD,by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  In this interview, John Burt reflects on his participation in the early days of NYUAD starting from 2009. He shares his impressions of Abu Dhabi and compares life in the downtown and in the outskirts of the city. John Burt reflects on the role of the UAE in his research in marine biology and ecology. He also shares the challenges of conducting research and teaching science in the early days of NYUAD, when the labs were situated in converted office space, later known as the Center for Science and Engineering. He talks about his participation in the admission of the first students, whom he describes as "dynamic" and "engaging". He shares his experience of teaching a class on Desert Ecology to the non-science-majors, in particular, conducting fieldwork in the desert in September. He takes pride in the growth of the students and brings an example in the person of Bethany Kolody, who started with the aforementioned class for non-majors but then excelled in natural sciences. John Burt shares a lot of excitement about relocating to the Saadiyat campus.
- Interview with Joshua Shirley by Ilka Datig (53:00), 4 May 2014; ADMC023_ref10; 53 minutes; 146.58 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref10)
  Video-recorded session with Joshua Shirley, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 senior student at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  Joshua Shirley reflects on his experience at NYU Abu Dhabi as part of the inaugural class. He talks about the process of getting to know his classmates from Candidate Weekend to graduation, as well as the process of learning about Abu Dhabi and its communities. Joshua mentions the groundwork done by himself and his classmates with regard to building mental health resources, Student Interest Groups, Athletics groups, networking and volunteering opportunities. Challenges at the university included the ever-changing academic policy, mental health, maintaining relationships across cultural contexts and the lack of anonymity in the community. His dearest memories include visiting Ethiopia with the football team, participating in the Yas Triathlon and the first open mic event.
- Interview with Nicole Lopez del Carril by Ilka Datig (37:00), 4 May 2014; ADMC023_ref11; 37 minutes; 100.38 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref11)
  Video-recorded session with Nicole Lopez del Carril, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 senior student at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  In this session, Nicole Lopez del Carril shares the story of her application process to NYU Abu Dhabi, including her experience of finding out about the university and visiting Abu Dhabi for the first time during the Candidate Weekend in 2009. She recounts her first impressions of the city and the difficulties associated with being the first generation of students at NYU Abu Dhabi, such as navigating the city and finding common grounds in building the community, including the creation of the Student Government Constitution. Nicole talks about her experience of engaging with the wider Abu Dhabi community through different initiatives, such as volunteering with ADvocacy and contributing to the Gazelle newspaper as a founding writer. She also reflects on the rapid change of Abu Dhabi, memory preservation in the UAE, student agency in the sphere of human rights in the country, and expresses her concern that different aspects of the community might get lost as a result of moving the university to Saadiyat Island.
- Interview with Ruben Polendo by Ilka Datig (55:00), 11 May 2014; ADMC023_ref12; 55 minutes; 149.05 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref12)
  Video-recorded session with Ruben Polendo, Executive Director of the Arts and Director of the Theater Program at NYU Abu Dhabi at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  In this interview, Ruben Polendo shares his first impressions of the Downtown Campus, including the challenges of teaching in the unfinished space. He recounts his expectations and first impressions of the first NYUAD students. Polendo shares the stories of multiple theater productions and their performances, such as CHAOS and The Ramayana. He discusses the challenges to the theater production in Abu Dhabi, such as the lack of equipment and the complicated relationship between the citizens and this type of art. He also reflects on the role of NYUAD in popularizing and transforming of the "theatrical ecosystem" in Abu Dhabi over the years, and the theater's power to bring together people from different backgrounds. In addition, he discusses the relationship between the city of Abu Dhabi and an artist, reflecting on the topics of inspiration, authenticity, and curiosity, as well as on the transformation of his own students over the years.
- Interview with Yannick Trapman-O'Brien by Ilka Datig (35:00), 11 May 2014; ADMC023_ref13; 35 minutes; 96.7 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref13)
  Video-recorded session with Yannick Trapman O'Brien, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 senior student at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  Yannick Trapman-O'Brien reflects on his time at NYU Abu Dhabi in his final semester. He speaks about the tension involved in his decision to attend the university instead of his dream school, Candidate Weekend being the event to sway his choice. The adjustments to a new city and lifestyle are important to him, especially experiencing the growing pains of the new university which often involved poor facilities like plumbing and dining. He mentions his complicated relationship with the city and the UAE as a whole because of the weather, differing perspectives on labour issues and volunteering, as well as the fast pace of growth. He says that moments of connection including community open mic events, thanksgiving celebrations and dancing in the rain were able to ease his difficult experience at the university.
- Interview with Musbah Dilsebo Ormago by Ilka Datig (24:00), 11 May 2014; ADMC023_ref14; 24 minutes; 65.19 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref14)
  Video-recorded session with Musbah Dilsebo, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 senior student at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  Musbah Dilsebo reflects on his time at NYUAD in his final semester at the university. He talks about Candidate Weekend with the desert trip and camel-riding being the most memorable events. His introduction to the University entailed feelings of culture shock especially in the student-professor relationship and highly demanding classes. He offers insight to the beginnings of NYUAD Athletics as they formed a collegiate soccer team which Musbah fondly remembers brought major attention to him from the student body. He mentions the difficulties of writing, homesickness and becoming used to having academic weaknesses. The inaugural student government constitution, which Musbah helped to draft, is mentioned alongside the importance of the student body and NYUAD as an institution for the future of global education.
- Interview with Amani Alsaied by Ilka Datig (29:00), 11 May 2014; ADMC023_ref15; 29 minutes; 78.09 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref15)
  Video-recorded session with Amani Alsaeid, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 senior student at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  In this interview Amani talks about the difficulties and high points of her time at NYU Abu Dhabi. Her challenges included choosing a film major while she was expected to follow a different academic path as well as adapting to her new diverse environment, although she appreciated her ability to travel within her program, the close contact with administrators and professors, and other opportunities. The process of advocating for a space for women's only athletics including a gym and fitness classes, one which she spearheaded, is part of her legacy at the University.
- Interview with Alistair Blacklock by Ilka Datig (52:00), 11 May 2014; ADMC023_ref16; 51:58 minutes; 144.95 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref16)
  Video-recorded session with Alistair Blacklock, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 senior student at the time of the interview, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  Alistair reflects on his journey at NYU Abu Dhabi from a similar international high school experience. At the University, he became heavily interested in environmentalism and creative writing, and founded the university's independent student-led publication, The Gazelle. His challenges included adjusting to the large amounts of money spent at the institution, the culture of NYU Abu Dhabi exceptionalism, and the relationship between the University and the government. He notes the changing city landscape as Abu Dhabi had just begun to develop, alongside the ever-changing composition of the University as new faculty and students joined.
- Interview with Matthew Silverstein by Ilka Datig (40:00), 11 May 2014; ADMC023_ref17; 40 minutes; 107.1 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref17)
  Video-recorded session with Matthew Silverstein, Assistant Professor of Philosophy, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.